<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title/><link>https://dunklas.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 05:21:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dunklas.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Custom resources with AWS CDK</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/aws/custom_resources_cdk/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 05:21:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/aws/custom_resources_cdk/</guid><description>CloudFormation custom resources is a great way to extend the functionality of CloudFormation. With custom resources you can run any custom logic in response to stack events. Example of use cases could be to create resources which CloudFormation has no support for, make requests to some external (non AWS) API, or maybe something not related to infrastructure at all, such as running a suite of smoke tests or seeding a database.</description></item><item><title>Properties of functions</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/functions_properties/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/functions_properties/</guid><description>In a previous post I covered some basic terminology of functions in a mathematical context. In this post, I will continue and explain some properties that a function may or may not fulfill.
One-to-one Consider a function $f: \mathbb{R} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}$ defined as $f(x) = x^2$. Note that $f$ can have an output value which has two different inverse images, e.g. $f(-3) = f(3) = 9$, but $-3 \ne 3$. This fact means that $f$ does not satisfy the property of being one-to-one, or injective.</description></item><item><title>Terminology of functions</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/functions_terminology/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/functions_terminology/</guid><description>In my job as a software developer I work with functions everyday, however I don&amp;rsquo;t really have much experience with functions in a mathematical context. My aim with this post is to cover some terminology of functions in a mathematical context.
A function is a process that relates every value in some set to a single value in some set. For example, suppose that $S$ is the set of all strings.</description></item><item><title>Independent events and conditional probability</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/conditional_probability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/conditional_probability/</guid><description>In Introduction to probability it was described how to calculate the probability of some event. However, the post only considered the probability of a single event. What if we want to know the probability of two events?
Independent events Imagine (again) that you&amp;rsquo;re to randomly pick a studio album by Black Sabbath, where it&amp;rsquo;s equally likely that you pick any of the studio albums. But this time, consider a scenario where you&amp;rsquo;re to pick two studio albums.</description></item><item><title>Foundations of probability, and expected value</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/probability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/probability/</guid><description>The idea of probability is to quantify how likely it is for some event to occur in some process or experiment. First, some definitions - The set of all possible outcomes in a process or experiment is refered to as a sample space, while an event is a subset of the sample space (i.e. one or more of the possible outcomes).
Given that $S$ is a finite sample space with equally likely outcomes, and that $E$ is an event in $S$, the probability of $E$, denoted $P(E)$ is defined as the number of desired outcomes divided by the total number of outcomes.</description></item><item><title>Counting subsets using r-combinations</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/counting_subsets_with_combinations/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/counting_subsets_with_combinations/</guid><description>Below are some examples of counting subsets with certain restrictions, using the concept of combinations, addition rule and difference rule.
Consider a scenario where, for the rest of your life, from the total of nineteen studio albums by Black Sabbath, you&amp;rsquo;re only allowed to listen to five of them. Without any restrictions to the selection, we can use 5-combinations to ascertain that the number of combinations you&amp;rsquo;d need to consider are: $${19 \choose 5} = \frac{19!</description></item><item><title>Combinations</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/combinations/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/combinations/</guid><description>In the area of combinatorics both combinations and permutations are central concepts. Both combinations and permutations relates to the selection of a number of elements from a set. What differentiates the concepts is whether the selection is ordered or not. In this post, I cover some fundamentals of what combinations are and how to count the number of combinations of sets.
Definition Combinations are unordered selections of elements from a set.</description></item><item><title>Counting number of elements in sets</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/counting_elements_sets/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/counting_elements_sets/</guid><description>Some counting problems can be solved by counting the number of elements in the result of a set operation, such as a union, difference or intersection. In below notes, the notation of $|A|$ is used for the number of elements (i.e. the cardinality ) of a set $A$.
The addition rule The addition rule can be used for counting the number of elements in a union of mutually disjoint sets (mutually disjoint means that the sets have no elements in common).</description></item><item><title>Permutations</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/permutations/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/permutations/</guid><description>In the area of combinatorics both combinations and permutations are central concepts. Both combinations and permutations relates to the selection of a number of elements from a set. What differentiates the concepts is whether the selection is ordered or not. In this post, I cover some fundamentals of what permutations are and how to count the number of permutations of sets.
Definition In contrast to combinations, permutations are ordered selections of elements from a set.</description></item></channel></rss>