<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Probability on</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/tags/probability/</link><description>Recent content in Probability on</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 22:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dunklas.github.io/tags/probability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Independent events and conditional probability</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/conditional_probability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/conditional_probability/</guid><description>&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/probability/">Introduction to probability&lt;/a> it was described how to calculate the probability of some event. However, the post only considered the probability of a single event. What if we want to know the probability of two events?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="independent-events">Independent events&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Imagine (again) that you&amp;rsquo;re to randomly pick a studio album by Black Sabbath, where it&amp;rsquo;s equally likely that you pick any of the studio albums. But this time, consider a scenario where you&amp;rsquo;re to pick &lt;strong>two&lt;/strong> studio albums. Although, after you pick the first studio album you put it back in the pile, so it&amp;rsquo;s possible two pick the same studio album twice - What&amp;rsquo;s the probability that both of the albums you pick include Ronnie James Dio as vocalist?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Foundations of probability, and expected value</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/probability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/math/probability/</guid><description>&lt;p>The idea of probability is to quantify how likely it is for some event to occur in some process or experiment. First, some definitions - The set of all possible outcomes in a process or experiment is refered to as a &lt;strong>sample space&lt;/strong>, while an &lt;strong>event&lt;/strong> is a subset of the sample space (i.e. one or more of the possible outcomes).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given that $S$ is a finite sample space with &lt;em>equally likely&lt;/em> outcomes, and that $E$ is an event in $S$, the probability of $E$, denoted $P(E)$ is defined as the number of desired outcomes divided by the total number of outcomes.
$$P(E) = \frac{|E|}{|S|}$$
Where $|E|$ indicates the number of elements in $E$, and $|S|$ indicates the number of elements in $S$.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>