<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>development on</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/tags/development/</link><description>Recent content in development on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 07:31:20 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dunklas.github.io/tags/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Structured Approach to Work With Software Development Tasks</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/structured-approach-to-sw-tasks/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 07:31:20 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/structured-approach-to-sw-tasks/</guid><description>Sometimes I see people (myself included) working on software development tasks in a non-structured way. You might have a vague understanding of what you&amp;rsquo;re about to accomplish. Aimlessly traversing the code base, hoping to find places that you might need to change. You instantly start to chase new ideas, while forgetting about prior (and possibly important) ideas. It might be hard to determine when you&amp;rsquo;re done. You might not commit intermediary working states, and have a hard time finding what you&amp;rsquo;ve messed up once something is broken.</description></item><item><title>Why you should keep a developer diary</title><link>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/why-dev-diary/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 05:33:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dunklas.github.io/posts/why-dev-diary/</guid><description>Every software developer should keep a diary.
Personally I&amp;rsquo;ve kept one for about a year now, and I&amp;rsquo;m very content. During some periods I haven&amp;rsquo;t bothered, and that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I can always write a new entry tomorrow, or next week.
The diary can cover a lot of different aspects from your daily work. Below are some examples.
Things you&amp;rsquo;ve learned Accomplishments that you&amp;rsquo;re proud of Thoughts on dynamics within your team Sketches of ideas Reasoning behind technical decisions Solutions to problems that you&amp;rsquo;ve struggled with I think the greatest benefit of writing a diary is that you give yourself time to reflect on your daily work.</description></item></channel></rss>